Register of the David Chubov Papers, 1905-1963
Hoover Institution Archives
David Chubov Papers
1905-1963
2000C17
Hoover Institution Archives
2 microfilm reels (0.3 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to resettlement of White Russian veterans and displaced persons after the Russian Civil War, and to Russian émigré affairs and activities of the Russian Orthodox Church abroad.
Chubov, David, 1878-1956
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biography
Fr. David Chubov was born on 24 June 1878. In 1901 he completed a course of studies at the Stavropol' Seminary, and in 1902 was ordained a priest, serving at a village church in Novoshcherbinovskaia stanitsa of the Kuban' Cossack region from 1904 to 1915. From January of that year until late 1917, he served as a chaplain on the Caucasus Front, primarily as the regimental priest of the 22nd Caucasus Rifles.
Witnessing the ensuing Civil War on the Kuban', Chubov was evacuated from Novorossiisk to Serbia with the departing White Army in March 1920. After a brief final return to the Crimea later that year, he was once again evacuated to Bulgaria, where from 1921 to 1932 he served as a priest in Sliven. From 1932 to 1936, Chubov served in various parishes in France and Brussels, until being assigned to the Church of the Protection of the Holy Virgin in Zürich, Switzerland, where he remained until his death. During and after the Second World War, he extended aid to Russian displaced persons, Ostarbeiters and POWs, helping many to emigrate to South America. Chubov died in Zürich on 14 August 1956.
Biographical Note
1878 June 24 Born, Staroshcherbinovskaia stanitsa, Kubanskaia oblast', Russia
1901 Graduated, Stavropol'skaia Dukhovnaia Seminariia
1904 Priest, Novoshcherbinovskaia stanitsa, Kubanskaia oblast'
1915 Priest, 1st Opolchenie brigade
1916 Priest, 22nd Kavkazskii strelkovyi regiment
1921 Archpriest, Sliven, Bulgaria
1932 Archpriest, Annecy, France
1936 Archpriest, Zürich, Switzerland
1956 August 14 Died, Zürich, Switzerland
Scope and Content
This collection consists largely of the correspondence of Rev. David Chubov, as well as of collected materials relating to anti-communist propaganda and activities and to Church affairs (1920s-1950s). The correspondence relating to the resettlement of Russian displaced persons and the interned troops of Gen. B. A. Khol'mston-Smyslovskii's anti-Soviet military force (1946-1948) is particularly significant, as are many of the rare brochures and leaflets issued by various Russian émigré organizations.
The collection includes some additional material donated by Chubov's secretary, Sofia Izler, after his death.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials and copyright to them (with some exceptions) are the property of the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russia.; Bulgaria.; France.; Refugees.; Russians in foreign countries.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Veterans.; Soviet Union.; Switzerland.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1905-1963.; Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Autobiography, correspondence, identity documents and other materials arranged alphabetically by physical form
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1923-1953.; Box 1
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Also includes several thematic files retained in original order (materials therein described in greater detail)
- WRITINGS, 1946 and undated.; Box 2
  Arranged chronologically by title
- WRITINGS BY OTHERS, 1936-1963.; Box 2
  Arranged alphabetically by author
- SUBJECT FILE, 1926-1955.; Box 2
  Brochures, leaflets and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject heading
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1945-1950 and undated.; Box 2
  Ten prints depicting Chubov, family members, Church hierarchs, and various subjects, as well as two postcards depicting Nicholas II and Alexander III
- Biographical File, 1905-1963
  - Autobiography, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - orrespondence. Mainly correspondence of A. S. Loukashkin with Rev. M. Pol'skii, Rev. D. Chubov, and his secretary, Sofia Andreevna Izler, regarding the disposition of Chubov's archive, 1956-1963 (Folder 2)
    - Identity paper, 1905 (Folder 3)
    - Inventory of archival materials (Folder 4)
    - Programs (Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1923-1953.
  General note
  See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Correspondence
  - General
    - "Perepiska s podsovetskimi liud'mi v Evrope." Consists of correspondence of various unidentified individuals. Includes cover letter by Chubov addressed to Iakov Iakovlevich (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Pereselenie v Argentinu." Concerns Chubov's involvement in the resettlement of Russian refugees, soldiers, and officers of Gen. B. A. Khol'mston-Smyslovskii's detachment from Liechtenstein to Argentina. Includes correspondence with numerous Russians and foreign officials, lists of candidates for resettlement, and other related documents
        - 1946 (Folder 7)
        - 1946-1947 (Folder 8)
        - 1947-1948 (Folder 9)
      - Untitled bound file of correspondence with N. E. Markov, Dowager Empress Mariia Feodorovna (signed by her secretary Pr. Dolgorukii), Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duchess Anastasiia, Metropolitan Antonii, Prince N. L. Obolenskii, A. P. Kutepov, A. F. Trepov, B. Serafimov, P. N. Krasnov, Ivan S. Shmelev, A. Kartashev, Also includes documents relating to the support of the Russian community in Sliven for anti-communist activities, 1923-1928, 1923-1949. (Folder 10)
    - Bardygin, Nikolai Mikhailovich, 1953 (Folder 11)
    - Boris III, King of Bulgaria, 1924 (Folder 12)
    - Sitnikova, Olimpiada Semenovna, et al., 1943 (Folder 13)
    - Surguchev, Il'ia D., 1953 and undated (Folder 14)
- Writings, 1946 and undated
  - "Za kem my poidem?" Typescript, attributed to Chubov by A. S. Loukashkin, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Pravda o masonstve," 1946. Typescript. Includes negative photostat of article by Iu. F. Semenov, "Vlast' nad dushami," Rossiia, and note on Semenov's and M. M. Fedorov's affiliation to freemasonry, 1947 March (Folder 2)
- Writings By Others, 1936-1963.
  Contains primarily unpublished holographs and typescripts, with some mimeographed texts
  - Eike, Vera Borisovna von. "Ekh, brattsy!" Typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Kostanda, Apostol Aleksandrovich. "Istoriia ikony Blagoveshcheniia, pozhertvovannoi Khramu-Pamiatniku Imperatora Nikolaia II v Briussele," Includes correspondence and related texts, [1953]. (Folder 4)
    - Kotliarevskii, N. M. Speech about Nicholas II, Typescript, 1936 February 2. (Folder 5)
    - Shmelev, Ivan S. Letter to S. A. Izler, 1963 (Folder 6)
    - Unidentified. "Iudin grekh," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 7)
    - Unidentified [D. Slavskii?]. "Malen'kaia russkaia istoriia," ]. Holograph, [1944 April (Folder 8)
    - Unidentified. "Sovetskii Soiuz - ne Rossiia," Typescript, 1947 October. (Folder 9)
    - Unidentified. "Zakat khristianstva: Episkop Damaskin, ego zhizn' I bor'ba za pravoslavie," Typescript, 1944 December. (Folder 10)
- Subject File, 1926-1955.
  Includes brochures, leaflets and other printed matter
  - Displaced persons (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Eastern Orthodox Church (Folder 12)
    - Gogol', Nikolai (Folder 13)
    - Monarchism (Folder 14)
    - Orlov, Sergei (Folder 15)
    - Propaganda, Anti-communist. Materials published by various groups opposed to communism
      - Bratstvo russkoi pravdy (Folder 16)
      - Fond spaseniia Rossii (Folder 17)
      - Unidentified organization (Folder 18)
      - Miscellany (Folder 19)
    - Miscellany (Folder 20)
- Photographs, 1945-1950 and undated.
  - One photograph depicting Chubov's parents in the Kuban' region (n.d., probably pre-Revolutionary), one small photograph of Russian Orthodox Church hierarchs, six photographs depicting Gen. B. A. Khol'mston-Smyslovskii and Chubov performing religious services for the former's troops interned in Liechtenstein one photograph depicting cadets of the Versailles Cadet School, one photograph depicting N. Vorob'eva's farm in Buenos Aires (1950) and two postcards depicting Nicholas II and Alexander III, (1945-1946) (Box 2, Folder 21)